hey everybody Welcome to the joy of
gymnastics I'm coach Joy today I am
joined by this lovely lady next to me
Lily we're going to be taking you step
by step through some really important
tumbling tricks here today um forward
rolls backwards rolls it's going to be
really easy and it's going to help you a
lot so we're going to have a lot of fun
let's go ahead and stand up and if you
have a mat like this um or if you're
outside on the grass great we're going
to come to the
edge so Lily if you wouldn't mind just
stpp to the side real quick I'm going to
show you guys how to do a forward roll
how we normally begin I'm going to show
you guys nice and slow here and then
we're going to go through this with Lily
um we're going to start in what we call
as gymnast a mountain pose so I'm
standing with my feet about hips
distance apart my hands come down just
under my shoulders so now I'm in
mountain when I'm here I'm really strong
my hands are strong fingers are spread
wide I'm going to tuck my chin to look
up at my belly button so I always say
look for your belly
button then once we're looking at our
belly button I'm slowly going to bend my
arms until I place just between my
shoulder blades right on the mat so as I
slowly roll through then I'm going to
bring my legs out in front of me and
then reach to stand up so now we're
going to walk you through this step by
step with Lily a few times again if you
have like some couch cushions to put
down if you could practice on the grass
somewhere soft um and it also always
helps to have a spotter with you as
well so Lily's going to stand reach down
into her Mountain hands are just beneath
her shoulders because you want to be
able to fit through your arms she's
going to tuck her chin to look up at her
belly button which are kind of pushes
her forward so she's going to actually
push forward through the legs bending
the elbows bending the knees into a tuck
and then pushing up to stand she's going
to reach those arms forward which helps
to lift her torso perfect liil let's go
ahe and do that two more times so taking
this really slow at home reaching
down tucking the chin to look up at the
belly button pushing through the legs
bending the elbows to place the backs of
the shoulders right on the mat coming to
a tuck Reaching Forward to help your
body stand up we want to avoid putting
our hands down would you mind showing
one where you put your hands down to
stand up please um it's okay to do that
in the beginning if you need to so you
can speed it up a little bit if you want
um tucking the chin looking at the belly
button pushing through using your hands
to stand up as you can see that's not
proper technique but if that's where
you're at in your practice that's all
right and then eventually you work to
really reaching those hands forward
which pulls the body up beautiful Lily
thank
you so then now we're going to go
through a backwards roll so kind of
similar but reversed so reaching the
arms up nice and Tall now we're facing
away from the mat she's going to reach
her bottom back bringing her hands down
and then rolling her spine back behind
her as you can see when she comes back
she puts her shoulders her hands just
underneath her shoulders can we do that
a little slow yeah all right so we're
going to break this down for you so arms
come up she sits her bottom back so
she's almost in a chair pose and then
now you can see her spine is already
rounded her knees are in a tuck she's
going to roll back one vertebrae when
she comes here can you stay in your plow
her elbows are bent and her hands are
just under her shoulders and then she's
going to continue to push through but
this is a little bit hard if you stop
you're going going to kind of stay stuck
um forward rolls backwards rolls you
kind of need your
momentum through it so thank you L let's
go a and show them one more time nice
smooth motion
here beautiful
salute sitting down reaching back
pushing those arms through to come and
stand
nice all right and then so for our final
tumble these are going to be our
straddle rolls so now we're going to
come back over to the front of our mat
now we're facing the mat we're going to
go for our strad rolls I'm going to move
out of the way because then I'd be kind
of blocking Miss Lily
here so this time we're standing um in a
straddle if you followed our last
flexibility video nice you know that a
straddle is your feet are wider apart
and then same motion as your forward
roll here but now with the legs
straddled we're going to reach down look
for the belly button pushing through the
legs to bend the elbows and rolling back
through beautiful so as you can see when
she came in to almost stand up she
brought her hands just in front of her
again which would allow her to continue
that straddle
roll beautiful so that part at the end
there it's probably the most difficult
you want to try that one more time and
freeze in that spot please
nice so here she really has to lift and
pull the hips up as she presses her
hands into the ground which would then
allow her to tuck her chin and continue
to roll through for a
second second forward roll
yay so when practicing your forward
rolls it's really important to remember
to protect your neck you don't want to
drop on your neck and these are really
great go-to tumbles to save you from any
tricks that might not have gone the
right way it's a great way to just kind
of bail out and keep yourself safe
without hurting your wrists or anything
like that so those are just a few of the
tumbles um that we can show you we're
going to show you one more after we do
some stretches and conditioning to help
you with your forward rolls and
backwards rolls um that's more of an
advanced trick but can also be a good
bailout if you practice your handstands
at all so we're going to actually get
into our Mountain pose right now you can
just go and sit up right
here so again feet are on the ground
hands are beneath the shoulders or just
a little bit wider you can make your
hands flat bab all the way into your
Mountain nice so now what Lily's going
to do is she's going to bend her elbows
pressing her head down and then back up
and she's going to practice this maybe
three to five times depending on how uh
how much strength you have in your
shoulders nice beautiful and then now
she can practice leg uh leg raises so
she's going to lift her heels lower lift
lower lift lower so this helps you get
used to that motion of pushing through
the legs coming more into the bringing
more of the weight into the
wrists and back down nice and then let's
do three to five donkey kicks you don't
have to kick all the way up to a
handstand here but stay keeping the
weight in the wrists
nice beautiful we're just pushing and
kicking off again getting our bodies
used to having a lot of our weight in
our arms and holding that
strength
beautiful and then now you can just go
ahead and take your legs out in front of
you seated and do a nice forward
fold yeah perfect really stretch the
back here nice round
spine if you can reach for your toes
great if you're holding on to your
ankles or knees no problem really pull
your body closer to your
legs wonderful it's going to help you
really stretch your back so you can roll
through getting your shoulders to the
floor instead of your neck or your head
very nice
little so now for our final kind of peak
uh tumble here again this is a little
more advanced something that you can
work up to we're going to try our
handstand for rolls so if you do have a
handstand practice or if you're
practicing away from the wall or if
you're facing the wall when you're
practicing this is a good way to kind of
bail out um if you need to or it's also
an awesome trick so all right so again
if you have a mat or if you're at home
or anything finding a nice safe
place Lil's going to come up to her
handstand and dropping through to the
forward
roll taada
you want to try one more time
perfect so do you mind if I come around
and kind of hold your handstand real
quick okay your hands more
here so if you have somebody that is
with you they can kind of help put you
into that position and then whenever
you're ready to roll through she bends
the elbows tucking the chin of course
and then rolling through to stand up all
right so just so you guys can really see
what we're doing here we're just going
to show you a few more times I'll keep
walking you through it so Lily's going
to kick up to her
handstand I can help Place her into a
nice spot here and then she's going to
slowly tuck the chin bending the elbows
tucking the knees to roll and sit up and
let's do maybe like one or two more
times how you feeling good feeling great
I love
it this time I won't I won't stop
you beautiful
standing up for that nice salute and
unas beautiful reaching tall extending
and coming into that tuck so also when
you're you're learning how to do these
tucks and all that this all translates
to your front tucks your back tucks um
all sorts of wonderful tricks so I hope
that this video has really helped you
the three major things to remember keep
keep in mind when you're practicing your
forward rolls is to really tuck the chin
you really want to look for your belly
button because if you drop on your head
you can hurt your neck and then trying
to really press through your arms and
push through the legs to roll through
instantly bend your knees so your feet
end up right next to your bottom and
reach forward to stand up tall okay um
if again if you have a friend with you
or anybody like that that can help spot
you or slow it down that's really great
um yeah we had a lot of fun so please
stay safe and we hope to see you again
[Music]